What happens when the world stops caring?
The Care Bears Movie is a adventure, fantasy,
animation film directed by Arna Selznick.
The Care Bears team up with a troubled brother and sister who just moved to a new town to help a
neglected young magician's apprentice whose evil spell book causes sinister things to happen.
Mr. Cherrywood (voice), played by Mickey Rooney.
Spirit (voice), played by Jackie Burroughs.
Love-A-Lot-Bear (voice), played by Georgia Engel.
Jason (voice), played by Sunny Besen Thrasher.
Friend Bear / Swift Heart Rabbit (voice), played by Eva Almos.
Funshine Bear / Share Bear (voice), played by Patricia Black.
The Care Bears Movie is a 1985 animated musical fantasy film directed
by Arna Selznick from a screenplay by Peter Sauder.
It was the second feature film made by the Canada-based studio Nelvana Limited after the 1983 film Rock & Rule, in
addition to being one of the first films based directly on a toy line and the first based on Care Bears.
It introduced the Care Bears characters and their
companions, the Care Bear Cousins.
The voice cast includes Mickey Rooney, Georgia Engel,
Jackie Burroughs and Billie Mae Richards.
In the film, an orphanage owner (Mickey Rooney) tells a story about the Care
Bears, who live in a cloud-filled land called Care-a-Lot.
While traveling across Earth, the Bears help two lonely children named Kim and Jason, who lost their parents in a
car accident, and also save Nicholas, a young magician's apprentice, from an evil spirit's influence.
Deep within a place called the Forest of Feelings, Kim, Jason and their friends
soon meet another group of creatures known as the Care Bear Cousins.
American Greetings, the owners of the Care Bears characters, began
development of a feature film adaptation in 1981.
Later on, the greeting card company chose Nelvana to produce it and granted them the film rights to the characters, in addition
to financing the film along with cereal manufacturer General Mills and television syndicator LBS Communications.
Nelvana's founders were producers, with fellow
employee Arna Selznick directing the film.
Production lasted eight months, with a production budget of at least $2
million, and took place in Canada, Taiwan, and South Korea.
Carole King and John Sebastian contributed several songs for the film.
Though major American film studios passed on the project, newly established independent distributor The Samuel Goldwyn
Company acquired the distribution rights to the film and soon spent a record $24 million promoting it.
The Care Bears Movie premiered on March 24, 1985, in New York, and was released in North America on March 29,
1985; another Nelvana film, Strawberry Shortcake Meets the Berrykins, was released alongside it.
It received mixed reviews from critics, who raised concern over its potential as a
full-length advertisement for the title characters, among other aspects.
It went on to earn $23 million domestically, making it the highest-grossing Canadian film
during 1985 (with C$1.845 million), in addition to winning a Golden Reel Award.
With over $34 million in worldwide sales, it set a box-office record for Canadian and
non-Disney animation and has remained one of Goldwyn's largest-earning releases.
The film's success, which saved Nelvana from closing, helped
revive films aimed at children in the US market.
It has since been cited as inspiring a spate of toy-based animated and live-action features; the film was later followed by two sequels,
A New Generation (1986) and Adventure in Wonderland (1987), neither surpassing the original financially or critically.
The film explores themes of cloud, sorcerer's
apprentice, spirit, woman director, kids.
The tone is lighthearted.